Guide to the Siobhan Nicolau Papers, 1968-1981
Department of Special Collections
Siobhan Nicolau Papers,
1968-1981
Special Collections M748
Nicolau, Siobhan
5 linear ft
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Gift of Siobhan Nicolau, 1995.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This collection contains papers amassed by Siobhan Oppenheimer-Nicolau during her tenure as Program Officer at the Ford Foundation. It includes important documentation chronicling the development of the Southwest Council of La Raza, the controversies surrounding the Mexican American Youth Organization and the Nixon administration crisis concerning bribery and influence brokering between federal employees and grant applicants from Hispanic community organizations. While the collection is primarily concerned with the formation of specifically Hispanic grant programs, other minority groups and public policy objectives are also represented within the Nicolau Papers. As a whole, these documents provide insight on the changing philanthropic goals of the Ford Foundation from the late 1960's through early 1980's, as well as the diversity of the applicants themselves.
Internal Ford Foundation Documents--including inter-office correspondence, memos, and discussion papers on policy issues targeted by the Foundation--comprise the first series in the collection. The second series, Nicolau Documents and Speeches, contains draft copies of informal addresses, as well as several drafts of a paper on the challenges facing Hispanic-Americans in the 1980s, through which the development of her own opinions on the appropriate role of philanthropy within the Hispanic community can be traced. The last series, Foundation Grants, makes up the bulk of the collection. It is loosely subdivided by subject, following the Ford Foundation's own identifications (as Delegated Authority Programs) where possible. Some series--particularly the Puerto Rico, Cuba, and Hispanics--overlap somewhat, either because of an applicant's more generalized outlook toward policy, or a change in the Ford Foundation's internal funding designations or record keeping. The folder titles within the series usually identify the target population: The Puerto Rican Defense Fund, for example, is clearly directed toward Puerto Ricans, although it is part of the Ford Foundation's Hispanics Delegated Authority Program.
CONTAINER LIST
- SERIES I: Ford Foundation: Internal Documents
  - Discussion Paper: CDC Evaluation (Apr. 13, 1973) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Discussion Paper: "Communities..." (Jan. 2, 1979) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cuban-Haitian Research Project materials and agendas (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Discussion Paper: Hispanics (Mar., 1984) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Foundation Grants to Hispanic Communities 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Affairs Meeting documents (Dec. 29, 1980) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ford Foundation Oral History Project (Feb. 6, 1973) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Statement: Program-Related Investments n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Statement: Responsive Philanthropy n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- SERIES II: Nicolau: Documents and Speeches
  - "All Our Children" n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "An Assessment of Three Chicano CDCs" (1979) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Council on Foundations: "One Foundation's View" (Mar. 30, 1981) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - memo: "Hispanics and 'the themes'" (Mar. 16, 1981) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Hispanics in the 1980's" (Apr. 25, 1980) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Hispanic-Americans in the 1980's "(May 5, 1980) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Hispanic-Americans in the 1980's September, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Hispanics" (Oct. 10, 1980) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "An Overview of U.S. Hispanics" (Nov., 1980) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "New Girl in Town" (Mar. 26, 1971) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "People Power" (Aug. 22, 1970) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - memo: "Squirming in the Puerto Rican Chairs" (May 28, 1976) (Box 1, Folder 21)
- SERIES III: Foundation Grants (By Subject)
  - Subseries: Center for Applied Linguistics (CAL)/ NICTAC
    - CAL; Bauman report on ESL for refugees (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - CAL; correspondence (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - CAL; refugee and ESL documents (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - CAL service contract (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - NICTAC meeting, Arlington, VA Jun. 18, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subseries: Community Development Corporations (CDCs)
    - Ford Evaluation: H.E.L.P. (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    - Mexican-American grants: 1977 (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Mexican-American grants: 1977 (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Chicanos por la Causa (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Chicanos por la Causa (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - East Bay Asian Development, Inc (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - H.E.L.P. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - La Jara Feedlot Scandal (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Mexican American Unity Council (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Mexican American Unity Council Adams-Kravitz consultancy (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Pilipino Bayanihan, Inc. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Spanish-Speaking Unity Council (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - TELACU (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - TIEMPO (cf Chicanos por la Causa) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Subseries: Cuba DAP (Delegated Authority Program)
    - Cuba DAP: correspondence (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Cuba DAP: proposals (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Cuba DAP: Cafferty and Krachan file (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Cuba DAP: Circulo de Cultura Cubana, Inc. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Cuba DAP: El Dialogo (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Cuba DAP: Bill Ravanesi (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Cuba DAP: Nelson Valdes monographs (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Cuba DAP: Nelson Valdes proposals and correspondence (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Subseries: Hispanics DAP
    - Ford Foundation: Hispanics; general (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Hispanic DAP Consultancy (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Pastora Cafferty Consultancy (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - La Casa de Puerto Rico (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Colorado Seminary (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Council on Foundations/Hispanic Advisory Center (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Maria Diaz-Perez: travel and study (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Paula diPerna on child labor (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Florida Lutheran Council (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Fordham University conference on Hispanic women (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Harvard U. Puerto Rico conference (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Hispanic-American Career Resources, Inc. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Hispanic Office of Planning and Evaluation, Inc. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Incine (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Inquilinos Baricuas en Accion (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - KCET grant (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Latino Institute (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Latino Projects, Inc. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Minority Rights Group (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Misericordia Hospital: bilingual materials (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - National Hispanic Leadership conference (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - National Organization for Migrant Children (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - NY State Department of Civil Service (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - El Nuevo Teatro Pobre de America (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Puerto Rican Legal Defense Fund (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - La Raza TV Consultant (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Solaridad Humana (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Stepan Conference at Yale U. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Taylor Institute (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - University of Illinois at Urbana: Mexican Women Immigrants (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - U. of Mass. exchange program with Puerto Rico (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Travel and Study: Willie Velasquez (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Subseries: Immigration DAP
    - Ford Foundation Immigration proposal evaluations: 1975 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Caribbean migration study (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Cuban Odyssey (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Barry Chiswick travel & study grant (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Florida International University (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Ginzberg Study at Columbia U. (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - National Opinion Research Center (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - National Organization for Migrant Children (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - NYC Human Resources Committee on Refugees (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - One Stop Immigration Center, Inc. (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Stanford Conference on Cuban/ Haitian Exodus (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Alex Stepick travel and study (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Washington Lawyers for Civil Rights (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Subseries: Indochinese Refugees
    - Ford Foundation: Indochinese Refugees; general (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Indochinese Refugees--correspondence (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Indochinese Refugees--documents (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Cultural and Service Center (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - IndoChina Refugee Action Center, 1981--proposal (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - IndoChina Refugee Action Center, 1981-- supporting documents (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Intergovernmental Committee for Migration (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - KCET-TV: "The New Americans" (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Refugee Women's Project (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Refugee Women's Project: correspondence (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Martha Stuart Communications, Inc. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - World Education Proposal (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Subseries: MAYO/La Raza
    - Mexican-Americans; general (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - 1968; MAYO and Southwest Council of La Raza (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - 1969; MAYO Jan.-Mar. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - 1969; MAYO April-May (2) (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
    - 1969; MAYO Jun.-Jul. (2) (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - 1969; MAYO August-Dec. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1969; MAYO correspondence (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1969; MAYO documents (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1969; MAYO newspaper coverage (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1969; MAYO reports (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 1969; MAYO Wilkins report (Ford foundation) (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 1969; MAYO 1970 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 1969; MAYO 1971 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - La Raza grant: 1972 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - La Raza grant: 1973 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - La Raza grant: 1974 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - La Raza grant: 1975 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - La Raza grant: 1976 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - La Raza grant: 1977 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - La Raza grant: 1979 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - La Raza grant: 1980 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - La Raza grant: Marumoto/ Nixon administration crisis (1973) (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - La Raza grant: (1974) (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - La Raza grant: Project Evaluation: "Not by Pride Alone..." (1969) (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - La Raza grant: Project Evaluation: "A Lower Profile..." (1972) (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Willie Velasquez (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Subseries: National Rural Fellows
    - National Rural Fellows: Background Materials (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - National Rural Fellows: May 6 luncheon (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - National Rural Fellows: "Capacity Building" report 1981 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - National Rural Fellows: prior grants to League of Cities (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - National Rural Fellows: 1978 proposal (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - National Rural Fellows: Third Party Intervention (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Subseries: Native Americans
    - Alaska Native Foundation (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - American Indian Development Association (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - American Indian Historical Society (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Boston University Trustees Film Proposal (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Central Council of the Tlingit and Haida Indians (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Hawaiian Coalition of Native Claims (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Indian Education Training, Inc. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Indiv. grant: Roxanne Ortiz (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Museum of the American Indian (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - National Conference of State Legislatures (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Navajo Community College (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Oklahomans for Indian Opportunity (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Clair Reiniger grant for Designwright (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - The Youth Project (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Subseries: Puerto Rico
    - Ford Foundation: Puerto Rico; general (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Aspira (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Aspira: Universidad Baricua (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Aspira: CEREP (Centro de Estudios de la Realidad Puertoriqueno) (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Aspira: El Dispensario (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Aspira: Institute for Social Research (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Aspira: National Puerto Rican Forum (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Aspira: NY Council for the Humanities: Bird Film (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Aspira: Cesar Perales: consultancy for Hispanics paper (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Aspira: Puerto Rican Family Institute (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Aspira: Puerto Rican Forum (1975) (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Aspira: Puerto Rican Migration Research Consortium (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Aspira: Jane Morrison: Angelita (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Aspira: Research and Resources (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Aspira: Wilson Center conference (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Subseries: Social Service/Public Policy
    - American Friends Service Committee (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Arizona Job Colleges (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Janet Curow on community-based organizations (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Human violence study at Vanderbilt U. (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Institute for Social Research (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - International Council of Voluntary Agencies (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - National Farmworkers Service Center (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - National Urban Fellows Career Planning Institute (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - National Urban Coalition Secretariat (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - San Diego State U. on U.S./Mexico border cities (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - SER- Jobs for Progress (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Southwest Voter Registration Education Program (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Women and Foundations/Corporate Philanthropy, Inc. (Box 10, Folder 21)